<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A general epistle to all Friends who are convinced of the truth. With a word of exhortation to Friends, to be diligent in keeping their mens &amp; womens meetings, for the service of truth; with a testimony to the same. : Also, an invitation to all that come to our meetings to hear the truth declared, no to rest in hearing, but to come into obedience thereunto, that so their souls may be saved. / By Samuel Cater.</title>
            <author>Cater, Samuel, d. 1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171110</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578228</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578228</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2616:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A general epistle to all Friends who are convinced of the truth. With a word of exhortation to Friends, to be diligent in keeping their mens &amp; womens meetings, for the service of truth; with a testimony to the same. : Also, an invitation to all that come to our meetings to hear the truth declared, no to rest in hearing, but to come into obedience thereunto, that so their souls may be saved. / By Samuel Cater.</title>
                  <author>Cater, Samuel, d. 1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Sowle, and are sold at his shop in Devonshire New-buildings, near Bishops-Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A General Epiſtle TO ALL FRIENDS Who are Convinced of the TRUTH. With a Word of Exhortation to Friends, To be diligent in keeping their Mens &amp; Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Meetings, for the Service of Truth; With a Teſtimony to the ſame. Alſo, an Invitation to all that come to our Meetings to hear the Truth declared, not to reſt in hearing, but to come into Obedience thereunto, that ſo their Souls may be ſaved.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Cater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Andrew Sowle,</hi> and are ſold at his Shop in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> New-buildings, near <hi>Biſhops-Gate,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:172173:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172173:2"/>
            <head>A General Epiſtle TO ALL FRIENDS WHO ARE Convinced of the Truth.</head>
            <p>MY Dear and Well-beloved <hi>Friends</hi> every where, who are the Called and Choſen of the Lord, to confeſs his Truth amongſt men, and to bear his Name in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the midſt of this Crooked and Perverſe Generation, amongſt whom the Lord hath planted us, who know not the Lord, neither are they acquainted with the Operation of his Hand, neither can they perceive what the Lord is now a doing, who hath begun a great Work in the Earth, which none can know whilſt they hate the Light, and live in Darkneſs, and rebel againſt God's good Spirit; from ſuch the Viſion is ſhut, and unto them the Book is ſealed, and the Sun is ſet, and Night and Darkneſs is upon them: But unto you that fear the Name of the Lord, on you the Son of Righteouſneſs is ariſen, according to the Promiſe, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord our God, by which you come to ſee the Way of the Lord, which the Wayfaring man Travels to the Kingdom of God by, which Light and holy Spirit of Truth, the Lord is revealing his ſecrets to them that fear him, and making known the great Myſtery of Life
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172173:3"/>and Salvation to all them that are turned unto him, and in their Hearts and Souls more deſire the encreaſe of the Knowledge of the Lord, than any thing this World can or doth afford: And to obtain this their Deſire, they are made freely willing to forſake Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, Wife and Children, Houſe and Land, and all that is near and dear to them in this World, that they may obtain Peace with God, through Jeſus Chriſt, while in this World, and in the World to come, Life Everlaſting: Oh! bleſſed of the Lord are you, and ſhall you be forever, who continue in this Mind, who ſee a ſhortneſs and an Emptineſs in all things without the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Fulneſs, who feeds the Hungry Soul with Bread from Heaven, and gives of the Water of Life to them that thirſt for it, through which the Lord refreſhes the weary Soul, and ſtrengthens the weak in their Journey, who are Travelling Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-wards.</p>
            <p>Oh! my dear Friends and Fellow-Travellers in this holy Way of the Lord, which God, through the Riches of his abundant Grace and Goodneſs, hath made known unto our Hearts and Souls, unto you it is upon me, in the Name of the Lord, to write to you all, in the tender Love of my God, and your God, whoſe powerful and pure Springs of divine Virtue at this time overcomes my Heart, and refreſhes my Soul, by which my Heart is tendred before the Lord, and my Soul refreſhed in my Bonds, in him, and in his pure Life, which even at this time moves upon my Heart, to write unto you in the tender Life and Love of our God, in which I have cauſe to believe it will be received by all that are in the ſame, in which I dearly ſalute you all, from the leaſt ſtirrings of this pure Life, to the greateſt Growth therein; for in this Life and Love of God is our Unity forever, which was before Death was, and ſhall be the Fortion of a Remnant, when Death and Darkneſs ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>And now unto you, my <hi>Dear</hi> and <hi>Elder Brethren,</hi> who have kept your Habitations in this pure Life, and grow up in it as Trees of Righteouſneſs, whoſe Fruits are holy and Leaves healing, and whoſe Life is in the pure Love of God, in which you have been made ſerviceable unto the Nations, and a Bleſſing in the Hand of the Lord, unto the People; for by you many have been turned unto
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172173:3"/>the Lord, and into the Right Way, that were travelling in a Wrong Way; and the Weak and Feeble, by you have been ſtrengthened in the Way of God, who hath made you as Pillars in his Houſe, and Overſeers over his Flock, who do it Freely of a Willing Mind, for which you are worthy of double Honour for your Work's ſake, which is not the Honour of Men, by any Flattery or outward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, but the Honour which cometh from God alone, in the pure Order of Life, in Honour, preferring you before, who are ſo in the Truth, who have been as Enſamples to the reſt; and your Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Counſels have been Grave, Sound and Weighty unto the Younger in the Truth, and are of a good Savour and bleſſed Service to all that keep their Habitations in the Truth, and retain the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Life, and bow to the Law of God, which is pure and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual: But as for them that have caſt off their firſt Love, and have loſt Charity, which is the Bond of Peace, it is not to be heeded what they ſay, who are gone from the Simplicity of the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, into Craft and Subtilty, they are gone from the Root; and although they may make a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for a time, yet a Withering will come upon them, and they ſhall be made to know, that Gods Love is unto you that have and do keep your Habitation in the Truth, and alſo muſt acknowledge it, if ever they return unto him, from whom they have fallen.</p>
            <p>And now, all dear <hi>Friends, Brethren</hi> and <hi>Siſters</hi> every where, who are turned to the true Light of Jeſus Chriſt, and believe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, in it wait upon the Lord continually, that by it you may always ſee your way, in which you ought to walk, and feel God's Power to preſerve you inoffenſively before the Lord, and that you may be Harmleſs towards all men; for in this pure Light, Wiſdom's Poſts come to be known, whereby all are to wait for Counſel and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that attend daily upon God, and come to receive the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (that is above the Wiſdom of the World) which is needful for every one to know; which Wiſdom cauſeth the Face to ſhine, and the Hearts of them that receive it to rejoyce in the Lord, who is the Fountain from whence it comes, for by it the Lord directs and guides in his own Way, that is Well-pleaſing unto him, and in which our Hearts and Souls receive and enjoy true Peace with God,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172173:4"/>which none can take away from us, bleſſed be his holy Name: Alſo, in this the Lord prepares and enables all that receive it, and depend thereupon, and are guided thereby, to bear a faithful Teſtimony for the Lord in Times of Tryals, Exerciſes and Sufferings; for although the Lord ſuffers his Children to be tryed through manifold Tryals and Exerciſes, which attend us for his Name and Truth's ſake, yet his Loving-kindneſs he will never with-hold from thoſe that truly truſt in him. And this, dear Friends, the Lord hath made us living Witneſſes of, whereby a Remnant can ſay, through a good and comfortable Experience of the Lords Mercy and Goodneſs unto our Souls and Hearts, even as in dayes paſt, <hi>In all our Afflictions he is Afflicted: And the Angel of his Preſence ſaveth us.</hi> And therefore have we cauſe to love the Lord, who hath heard our Cryes; for by his Arm he hath gathered us, and by his Power he hath and doth preſerve us; and in his holy Light, which is the Way of Life and Salvation, the Lord is leading and guiding of us unto his holy Hill and everlaſting Reſt, which is the Lot and Portion that the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in all all Ages deſired and ſought after, whom God viſited with the Day of his Mercy, in which their Souls rejoyced; as Chriſt ſaid of <hi>Abraham, He ſaw my Day, and was Glad:</hi> And how greatly did <hi>Zacharias, Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> rejoyce and praiſe God, when he viſited them? and <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Hannah,</hi> with many more, when the Lord viſited them with the Day ſpring from on high, they rejoyced in it, and ſpoke of it unto all that looked for Salvation, which Day was Chriſt, coming and appearing unto them; for in him and by him are all things received, that the Honeſt and Upright-hearted, that fear God, can deſire; for he is the Seed of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that bruiſes the Serpents Head, and overcomes Death, and brings Life and Immortality to Light, in the Soul that waits for it; for on him the Help is laid, who ſaves to the uttermoſt all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and obey him; for in him all Fulneſs dwells.</p>
            <p>And now, all Tender-hearted <hi>Friends,</hi> whom the Lord hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited your Souls, as he did his Servants and Hand-maids in days paſt, with the Day-pring from on High, this is the word of Exhortation that lives upon my Heart unto you, Oh! wait upon the Lord to ſee the Work of God, by Jeſus Chriſt, wrought and made known in all your Hearts, that what is not of him, you may ſee overcome by him,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172173:4"/>and brought down by his Power into the Death, that ſo you may all, that are convinced by the Truth, witneſs a dying unto Sin, and come to live unto Righteouſneſs through him; and having put off, as concerning your former Converſations, the old Man, with his Deeds; and having parted with your own Righteouſneſs, which is the Phariſees Clothing, and put on the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt Jeſus, which is the Saints Clothing, you are thereby prepared to ſhew forth the Praiſe of God, whilſt you are here, and alſo ſhall thereby be prepared to enter into his Glory, where your Souls ſhall reſt with the Lord, and pertake of that Feaſt that he hath prepared for all that deny themſelves and follow Chriſt, and forſake their own Wills and obey the Will of God; for you are they that have the Wedding-Garments, and having Oyl in your Lamps, by which your Light ſhines before men, whereby God is glorified; for his Light doth not only ſhine in your Hearts, whereby it becomes your Guide, but it alſo ſhines through you unto others, that are yet in Darkneſs; whereby Chriſts words come to be fulfilled, who ſaid to them that believed in him, <hi>Ye are the Light of the World and the Salt of the Earth;</hi> for all that receive his Light and Grace into their Hearts, they are to Seaſon the Earth by their Savoury Lives and Upright Converſations, by which we do reach to the good in all, and judge them that live in the Evil Converſation, whereby they ſhall be made in the Day of Viſitation to confeſs, That the Lord is with us of a Truth, who hath called us to bear witneſs thereunto, and to confeſs his Name before men, although for it we do ſuffer, as the Servants of God did in days paſt, who have ſaid, <hi>That it is not given to us only to believe, but alſo to ſuffer:</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Yea, and all that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer Perſecution;</hi> which we ſee is now fulfilled in a Remnant, who love the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al their Hearts; for there is many that profeſs Chriſt Jeſus, that ſuffer nothing for him; but thoſe that leave the Glory of the World, and the Sin-pleaſing Pleaſures of the Fleſh, and follow Chriſt, they muſt and do ſuffer under them that live in it; and them that leave the Teachings of Corrupt and Carnal men, and wait to be taught of God, they muſt ſuffer; and they that bear a faithful Teſtimony againſt Idolatry, and the Superſtitious Wayes and Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that the Prieſts and People have invented, in their dark Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172173:5"/>who make void the Command of Chriſt, through their Traditions, as their fore-Fathers, the Phariſees, did the Law of God, ſo do they now, the Worſhip of God in Spirit and in Truth; and they that Worſhip God therein, they muſt and do ſuffer by this Generation, as the People of God did under the Scribes, Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees and Perſecutors in dayes paſt, who perſecuted Chriſt, and called him, <hi>A Deceiver,</hi> and <hi>A Blaſphemer;</hi> and who perſecuted the Apoſtles, calling them, <hi>Vain Babblers, and ſuch as turned the World <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſide down, and drew People from their Temples, and were not ſubject to their Law:</hi> Which is the Cry of the Prieſts now, againſt thoſe whom God hath brought forth in a Teſtimony againſt them; as the Upholders of <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple did, with all their Crafts-men, who were in a Rage againſt the Apoſtles, and cryed one unto another, <hi>Sirs, You know that by this Craft we have our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and if we let theſe men alone, all men will follow them, and then our Craft will come to nothing;</hi> much like the way of the Proud, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous and Envious Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Now, concerning the Servants and Meſſengers of the Lord, unto whom God hath made known his Light and his Truth, which was before they were, and ſhall be when they ſhall be no more; for God is ariſen, and is going on in his mighty Power, and by the ſtrength of his own Arm he will overturn all that ſtand in the Way of his Truth, and that oppreſs his Seed, and offend his little Ones that believe in his Name, for whoſe ſake the Lord is ariſen to plead the Cauſe of his afflicted Ones; for by ſtrength ſhall no man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail: <hi>For becauſe of Oppreſſion of the Poor, and the Sighing of the Needy, the Lord will ariſe for Deliverance, and bring down the lofty City</hi> Babylon, <hi>and lay her Honour in the Duſt; and her Merchants ſhall mourn, and her Lovers ſhall lament and bewail her, for the Miſery that ſhall come upon her in the Day of the Lord determined:</hi> Which Day is dawned, in the Light of which, a Remnant ſee the Viſion is near to be fulfilled, that was ſeen of <hi>Babylon's</hi> Torments and her Merchants Miſery, that ſhall come upon her, and them that Trade with her; in which Day the Righteous ſhall rejoyce in the Lord, who hath ſaved and redeemed them out of her.</p>
            <p>And now, dear Friends, that are come out of <hi>Babylon, Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where the Righteous ſuffer, all be mindful of that Arm
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172173:5"/>that hath brought you out, and by which the Lord is leading you unto Everlaſting Reſt: There is great cauſe to be watchful, and always to wait to feel the Lord's Power to preſerve and keep you: For all that came out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> did not enter into the Land of Promiſe, ſome fell ſhort through Unbelief; and there was but four came out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and one of them looked back; and twelve fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Chriſt, and one of them betrayed him; and how many hath the Enemy betrayed in our Day, ſome in one thing, and ſome in another, for want of Watchfulneſs unto the Truth, in which there is Preſervation for all that love it, and are led and guided by it; For all Miſcarriages and Diſhonour that have been brought upon the worthy Name of the Lord, that is concerned amongſt us, and wrong done to any Man, by any that has and do profeſs the Truth, and come amongſt us, Truth is clear of it all, and is not to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but they, in that they have not ſtood in the Counſel of it, but have hearkned to the Serpent, as <hi>Eve</hi> did, and as <hi>Cain</hi> did, and <hi>Judas</hi> did, and as all that forſake the Lord do, and that they know, who have in any meaſure known the Work of God upon their Hearts, by the Truth; they know that in that there is no Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, but the Truth judges it all, and leads People out of all Unrighteouſneſs, that obey it: And therefore, bleſſed of the Lord are they that obey the ſame, for they only do and ſhall enjoy the Comfort of it, and have true Peace in it; as Chriſt ſayes, <hi>He that doth well cometh to the Light, and bringeth his Deeds to it;</hi> Whereby it appears that they are wrought in God, in whom the true Peace is, that Man cannot take away; and in which holy Light the true Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher comes to be ſeen and known that cannot be removed into a Corner, but our Eyes, that God hath opened, ſee him near to teach and guide us in the Way, that is well-pleaſing in his ſight; and great is the Peace of all that obey him.</p>
            <p>And all dear Brethren and Siſters, whom the Lord hath Called and Choſen, in your ſeveral places, to be a kind of firſt Fruits unto him, to bear forth his Name in Righteouſneſs, and ſhew forth his Praiſe, and to be Inſtruments in his Hand to ſtrengthen the Weak, and to ſupport the Feeble, and to refreſh the Bowels of the Poor, and to clothe the Naked, and to ſupply them that are in want, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Neceſſity, and your Ability, which is a Service ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172173:6"/>to God, and is truly profitable unto Men, and is a Duty that Truth requires for all to be diligent in, that have of the Things of this World; and the Apoſtles commend them that were diligent in it, and laid it as a Charge upon them, that were Rich in this World, not to be unmindful of their Duty in that good Work, and which the Love of God conſtrains all the faithful to be mindful of, now in this our day and time; for ſays Chriſt, <hi>The Poor you have alwayes with you.</hi> And now, that you may faithfully perform all thoſe good Services which the Lord requires of you, according to your Ability he hath and doth give unto you, all be diligent to keep your Mens and Womens Meetings, that are ſet up in the Power and Wiſdom of God, and is accompanied with the ſame, as there are many living Witneſſes can, and do teſtifie the ſame; even all that go to theſe Meetings, and keep them in the Simplicity of their Hearts and Souls, as hoping and believing they ſhall meet with that their Hearts and Souls deſire, which is the Preſence of the Lord, and them he doth not ſend empty away, as is well known to you, that according to the Integrity of your Hearts, he gives Wiſdom and Counſel, whereby he fits both Men and Women, and prepares them to perform what Service he hath for them to do in the Meetings, in which Meetings they have a good opportunity to clear their Conſciences. And caſe your minds one to another, when you have any thing lies upon you, and to ſtir up one another to the Performance of your Duties in your ſeveral Places and Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and to take notice of any that come amongſt us, and do not anſwer Truth in their Converſations, that they in the tender Life and Love of God may be dealt withal, and all other things which concern our Teſtimony may, in the ſavour of Life, be performed and carryed on, and the Poor may be relieved; and thus meeting in the Love of God, and being refreſhed with the ſame in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of your Duties and Services, return to your Father again in Peace. And why any ſhould be againſt either Men or Women, (for this, I know not) which love the Proſperity of <hi>Sion.</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but on the contrary there is true cauſe to Rejoyce, in that the Lord hath brought both Man and Woman into a true Capacity to ſerve him, and to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172173:6"/>unto another in his holy Truth, by which he hath brought, and is bringing both Man and Woman out of the Fall, into Chriſt that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fell, in whom Male and Female are all one, in whom is the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and by whom all come to be reſtored again into their Services, both Men and Women, and made helpful one unto another, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the outward Creation and Concerns, but alſo in the labour of the Goſpel and management of Truth's concerns; in which Work and Service, let all be diligent in the performance of it, as well Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as Men, all Eying your Head Chriſt Jeſus, from whom your Supply comes: And all be diligent in keeping your Meetings, and let none be diſcouraged, becauſe of any oppoſition you may meet withal, from thoſe that ſet themſelves againſt Womens Meetings, becauſe (they ſay) they ſee no Service in them; that is no Rule for you to walk by, and to neglect your Duties, becauſe they ſee no Service in them; neither is it a ſufficient ground for them that ſay ſo to oppoſe them, for ſuch ought to be quiet, and wait upon God in the Simplicity of their Hearts, out of all prejudice and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, to know the Mind of the Lord in this matter, ſeeing, <hi>viz.</hi> that by the ſame Power of God, by which the Goſpel hath been preached, Womens Meetings were gathered and ſettled; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſlights them, or the Service thereof, do and will come to loſs thereby, for the Lord is with them, who hath made them a Bleſſing in his Hand: For the Teſtimony of the Lord's requiring and owning of them plainly appears, in that his Power and Preſence hath been, and is, from time to time manifeſt amongſt his Servants and Hand-maids, when ſo met, as hath been largely teſtified unto by many antient and faithful Servants of Chriſt, which is great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to all that love Truth and Righteouſneſs, and that do deſire the proſperity of the Truth and of one another, therein to keep them, in the meek and quiet Spirit: and take heed of ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with them that are in the oppoſition, leſt you hurt your ſelves, and thereby burthen the tender Life in your ſelves, in which pure tender Life you ſhall out-live all Oppoſition, and that will dye and wither; for all that have not Nouriſhment from the Root, which is Chriſt, will dye of it ſelf, which we have ſeen from time to time.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:172173:7"/>
And therefore, all dear Friends, go on and keep your Meetings in the Name and Fear of the Lord, that you may ſtill feel his Power and Preſence amongſt you, and then it is no matter what any ſay againſt you; unto whoſe Power I commit you all, who deſires your Proſperity as my own, who can, and do teſtifie, that I have been truly refreſhed with the Power and Preſence of the Lord, both in Mens and Womens Meetings, by, and in which Power, the Lord hath laid a neceſſity upon me to bear my Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, That they are ſet up in the Power and Wiſdom of God; and bleſſed are they that keep them in the ſame, and they that oppoſe them, oppoſe the Work of God, and will come to loſs by it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>AND now, dear People, who come into our Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, from time to time, and hear the Truth declared, and are convinced in your Judgments by it, and your Underſtandings cloſes with it, and many times your Conſciences are awakened by the powerful preaching of the Word of Life, in which your Hearts are tendred, and the Eye of your Underſtandings then being opened, you thereby ſee your ſelves, and feel ſomething of the Preciouſneſs of the Truth declared; but for want of bowing thereunto, withal your Hearts and Souls, and giving up to be led and guided thereby, the Enemy prevails again, whoſe work it is to darken the Mind and cloſe the Eye, which God by his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Truth begun to open, whereby you may come to ſee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172173:7"/>the Way to Reſt, and then comes the Savour of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which you felt whilſt you were hearing the Truth, and whilſt the Tenderneſs remained upon you, to be loſt; whereby the Apoſtles words come to be fulfilled; <hi>Man hearing the Word and doth it not, is like unto a man behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his natural Face in a Glaſs, and preſently goeth away, and forgetteth what manner of man he was:</hi> ſo do many that hear the Truth forget or neglect to obey the ſame, without which no true and laſting Comfort can be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear People,</hi> I do not write in this manner to accuſe any of you, or becauſe I would have you leave coming to our Meetings, no; the Lord knows, but to clear my Conſcience, as a Friend to your Souls. I beſeech you to lay hold of the Scepter of Gods Mercy, while it is held forth unto you, and come away to the Feaſt, while the Door is open. Oh! how have I ſeen, both in City and Country, ſome that have come to our Meetings, in the time of Truth being declared, their Minds bowed and their Hearts broken before the Lord, ſo that I have been ready to conclude, That ſurely this Man or Woman muſt needs cleave to the Lord with all their Hearts, and obey his Truth, which now they are ſo much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with; but it hath too often proved otherwiſe, whereby Chriſt's words have been fulfilled, who ſayes, <hi>That after the Word is received with Joy, the Enemy comes and takes the Word out of their Hearts; and ſome for the love of the World, and ſome for fear of Perſecution, the good Seed, that begun to put forth, comes to be choaked, and thereby they are made Unfruitful;</hi> But the Honeſt receive the Seed, which is the Truth, into their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172173:8"/>Hearts, and give up the ſtrength of their deſires unto it, they are made Fruitful unto God by it, and the Lord bleſſes them in it, and gives them Peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in this World, and Aſſurance of Glory in the World to come, which is more precious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, than all that can be parted withal for his ſake: Oh! that you therefore may come to be found Doers of the Will of God, and not Hearers only, is the Deſire of my Soul for you all; for this is the Day of your Viſitation, in which the Lord is calling of you, and ſtriving with you, to gather you unto himſelf; that ſo you may come to be made pertakers of his Everlaſting Riches that fadeth not away, which is the Portion I deſire for your all, and which is the Feaſt you have been often invited unto, in the Name of the the Lord, by his Servants and Meſſengers. Oh! come away, for the Lord hath furniſhed his Table; and if you make Excuſes, and will not come unto him, by turning unto his pure Light and Grace, which leads unto him, and obey the ſame, unto which you have been directed by his Servants, the Lord will be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, and you, through your own Neglect, will be ſhut out; and a People the Lord will have, that ſhall pertake of his free Mercies.</p>
            <p>So, dear People, prize your Time, whilſt you have it, and whilſt the Lord is ſtriving, and Chriſt is knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by his Convincements, by his Light in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, open unto him, that he may come in unto your Hearts, and that you by his Power may be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and enabled to ſerve the Lord, whilſt you are in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172173:8"/>this World, that you may reſt with all his Redeemed Ones, when Time ſhall be no more here; then ſhall my Deſire be anſwered in writing to you in this manner, which is my true Deſire for you all, who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your True Friend, <hi>Samuel Cater.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Elye</hi> Priſon, where I am a Sufferer for my Obedience unto the Lord, under the Corrupt Wills of men, becauſe I cannot for Conſcience ſake diſobey the Command of Jeſus Chriſt, nor joyn with the Prieſts in their Carnal and Dark Way of Worſhip, <date>
                     <hi>the 6th Moneth,</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
